Guide to the Mrs. Field's Literary Club records 1995.004
Brooklyn Historical Society
Mrs. Field's Literary Club records
circa 1880 to 1995
Center for Brooklyn History
Mrs. Field's Literary Club (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
1995.004
4.8 Linear Feet in eleven manuscript boxes and one small flat box.
6 Cassettes in one small flat box.
This collection contains materials generated by the Mrs. Field's Literary Club, a club for women founded in 1884. The collection includes correspondence, minutes, programs, essays, photographs, and audio cassettes from meetings and events.
Conditions Governing Access
Per donor agreement, materials dated through 1950 are currently open to researchers without restriction, but access restrictions apply for later materials in the collection. Materials dating from the 1950s will be open to researchers in 2025, materials dating from the 1960s will be open to researchers in 2035, materials dating from the 1970s will be open to researchers in 2045, and materials dating from the 1980s will be open to researchers in 2055.
Conditions Governing Access
The collection may only be used in the library and is not available through interlibrary loan.
Due to preservation concerns, the audiocassettes in Box 12 are not open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. Field's Literary Club, 1996.
Arrangement
The collection is in chronological order.
Historical Note
The Mrs. Field's Literary Club was founded in 1884 by Mrs. Mary J. Field (Mrs. George White Field) as a social club for her students and other women in the Brooklyn Heights neighborhood of Brooklyn. The purpose of the Club is to bring "together members of Mrs. Field's Club for literary culture and for social discourse." The social meetings of the Club generally took place monthly at members' residences during which members presented essays on literature, art and music, or performed plays. Writers and educators who were not members of the Club have also been invited to present at meetings, such as Pandita Ramabai, William Butler Yeats, and Arthur S. Hardy. The Mrs. Field's Literary Club inspired the formation of the Twentieth Century Club, another Brooklyn-based club devoted to appreciation of the arts and open to both men and women. The Mrs. Field's Literary Club is still active as of 2021.
Related Materials
The Center for Brooklyn History holds the following related collections:
- Brooklyn Clubs Collection, 1843-2005 (ARC.172)
The following published materials included in this collection are also cataloged in the Center for Brooklyn History Library's Main Collection:
- Mrs. Field's Literary Club. Mrs. Field's Literary Club: poetry meeting, April 3, 1941. 1941.
- Mrs. Field's Literary Club. A history of Mrs. Field's Literary Club. 1909.
Scope and Contents
This collection is made up of materials generated by the Mrs. Field's Literary Club from its founding in 1884 until the mid-1990s. The collection includes meeting minutes and financial records, as well as correspondence related to meeting attendance and invitations to guest speakers. Among those materials is a book of handwritten minutes and financial records related to meetings between the Mrs. Field's Literary Club and the Twentieth Century Club, dated 1893-1899.
Much of the collection is made up of materials from social meetings and anniversary events, including programs, menus, essays, play and presentation scripts, photographic prints and slides, audiocassettes with recordings of plays in the early 1980s, and a corsage from the centennial celebration.
The yearbooks, which span from 1884 to 1995, are booklets released annually and provide the constitution and by-laws, member directory, and listing of programs that took place that year.
Also included in the collection are a photographic portrait of Mrs. Mary J. Field and two copies of A History of Mrs. Field's Literary Club (1909), a book published on the occasion of the 25th anniversary of the club.
Separated Materials
A copy of A history of Mrs. Field's Literary Club (1909) was transferred to the Center for Brooklyn History's Library Main Collection.
Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Intellectual life; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) |x Social life and customs; Clubs -- New York (State) -- Kings County; Correspondence; Literature |x Appreciation |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Literature |x Societies, etc.; Minutes; Programs (documents); Mrs. Field's Literary Club (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- 1880-1894 (Box 1)
  - Assorted Undated Notes: Printed and Handwritten, circa 1884-1890 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Obituaries, circa 1884-1895 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Poems - Miss Tousey, circa 1884-1895 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Assorted Notes, circa 1880-1890 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Book of Poetry, 1881 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Picture of Mrs. Field, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - 4/3/84 First Programme of Mrs. Field's, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 5/1/84 Paper on Art, 8 pages, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - 12/4/84 Program, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Scientific Committee Report: Handwritten, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - 4/30/85 Wagner Theories, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 4/30/85 Reading by Mrs. Henry Bowen, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Handwritten Regret, 11/20/86, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 2/5/86 Handwritten Regret, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - By-laws, 1887 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters to Mrs. Field from Literary Figures, 1887-1897 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 4/5/88 A New Theory of Language: Handwritten Report, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 12/29/88 Handwritten Regret V. W. Higgenson, 1888 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 1/19/89 Handwritten Regret, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 1/20/89 Handwritten Regret Branden Matthews, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Constitution and By-laws of Mrs. Field's, 1884-1889 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Minutes, 1884-1890 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - 4/25/90 Handwritten Note Mary Mapes Dodge, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - 1/11/90 Handwritten Note Kate Douglas Riggs, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Handwritten List of Mrs. Field's Programs, 1884-1893 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "The Drama in Old Brooklyn" for Mrs. Field's, 4/4/89; March 1889, Handwritten Paper on English Drama (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Early History with Papers, circa 1890 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Minutes, 1890-1893 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - 11/19/91 Acceptance Grace Greenwood, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - 12/7/91 Handwritten Note: Henry Van Wyck, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - 11/29/92 Handwritten Regret, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Music Meeting, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - 11/30/92 Handwritten T. Harris Crawford Regret, 1892 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - 4/7/93 "Love Letters of a Worldly Woman," Original and Copy, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - 11/27/93 Regret, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - 12/2/93 Handwritten Regret, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Yearbook and Program, 1893-1894 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- 1893-1910 (Box 2)
  - Minutes, 1893-1897 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Program for Year, 3/1/94 Programme, 1894 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 5/7 Program, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - 4/4/95 Program, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper Articles, Programs, Letters, 1895 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - 3/5/96 and 4/9/96 Programme, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Programs, Letters, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Minute Book, 1897-1901 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Two Papers, Music Report, History of Club, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Minute Book, 1901-1905 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 3/16/03 Handwritten Acceptance: M. W. Weber, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Papers, circa 1890-circa 1910 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 19th Anniversary Year, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - 5/7/08 Resume of Club Year, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - 25th Anniversary Documents, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 25th Anniversary Documents, 1909 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- 1893-1909 (Box 3)
  - Yearbooks, 1884-1895 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - [Yearbooks], 1884-1899 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Mrs. Field's Literary Club at the Twentieth Century Club, 1893-1898 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Mrs. Field's Literary Club at the Twentieth Century Club, 1897-1899 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - [Yearbooks], 1900-1909 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - 25th Anniversary, History, Newspaper Clippings, 1908-1909 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - 1/7/09 Poetry, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 25th Anniversary Book, Photo, and Negative of Mrs. Field, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1905-1909 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Program, Thank You Note, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- 1911-1929 (Box 4)
  - Yearbooks, 1911-1914 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - [Yearbooks], 1915-1919 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - 5/4/16 Shakespeare Festival, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Verses for Occasions Maria L. D. Mallory, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Paper, "Thousand-Souled Shakespeare" Ida Prentice, 1916 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Minute Book, 1909-1912 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Minute Book, 1912-1915 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Minute Book, 1915-1919 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Poems by Members of Mrs. Field's (Read at February Meeting), 1918 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Original Poetry, 1920-1929 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Poetry, 1918-1920 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Minute Book, 1919-1923 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- 1923-1940 (Box 5)
  - Yearbooks, 1923-1929 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - [Yearbooks], 1936-1948 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Minutes, 1926-1932 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Minute Book, 1923-1926; 1923 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - [Eulogies and Correspondence], 1920-1929 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - 40th Anniversary Papers, circa 1924 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - 40th Anniversary, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - 40th Anniversary, 1924 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Yearbooks, 1935-1939 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Minutes of Social and Executive Meetings, 1932-1936 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - 50th Anniversary, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Mrs. Field's Death, 1934 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Paper on China, 1938 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Recording Secretary Minutes of Social Meeting, 1937-1940 (Box 5, Folder 14)
- 1935-1950 (Box 6)
  - Executive Committee Minutes, 1935-1940 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Programs, 1938-1939 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Brooklyn Botanic Garden Donation, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Brooklyn Safe Deposit Contents, 1939 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Topic Cards, 1940 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Financial Journal, Receipts, and Disbursements, 1939-1949 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - 4/3/41 Poetry Meeting, 1941 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Programs, 1941-1943 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Literary Club Minutes, Executive Board, and Annual Business, 1941-1944 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Recording Secretary Minutes and Social Meetings, 1941-1948 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Topic Cards, 1941-1949 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - 60th Anniversary, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Reports made at Annual Meetings, 1943-1946 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Handwritten Paper Mrs. A. Van Wyck, 1944 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Executive Board and Annual Business Meeting, Financial Ledger Notes, Treasurer's Report, 1943-1945 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Executive Board and Annual Business Meeting, 1946-1947 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Program Reports, Topic Cards, Poetry, 1946-1950 (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - 4/21/49 Nominating Committee, Executive Board and Annual Business Meeting, Treasurer's Report, 1948-1949 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Poetry from Mrs. Field's Members, 1945-1950 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Assorted Notes, 1946-1949 (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Yearbooks, 1941-1945 (Box 6, Folder 21)
- 1946-1959 (Box 7)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Materials dated 1951-1960 are closed for research until 2025.
  - Checking Account, 1946-1952 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Poetry from Mrs. Field's Members, 1951-1952 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - 2/5/52 Letter from Marianne Moore, 1952 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - 4/20/50 President's Report and Minutes, 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, Executive Board and Annual Business Meeting, 1952-1953 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1953 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Minutes, Executive Board and Annual Business Meeting, 1954-1955 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1955 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1956 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Executive Board and Annual Business Meeting, 1956-1957 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Mrs. Field's Manhattan Tour, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Minutes, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Programs, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Executive Board and Annual Business Meeting, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Minutes, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Programs, 1958 (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Programs, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - 1/9/59 75th Anniversary Meeting (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Minutes, 1959 (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Programs, 1955-1959 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Assorted Notes, 1951-1955 (Box 7, Folder 22)
  - 1950s Yearbooks, 1950-1959 (Box 7, Folder 23)
  - Tour of Old Dutch Houses Slides, circa 1959 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - Lecture on Old Houses Slides, 1957 (Box 7, Folder 25)
- 1960-1969 (Box 8)
  Materials dated 1961-1970 are closed for research until 2035.
  - Programs, 1961-1969 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 3/61 Paper Mrs. F. W. Blossom, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Program, 1961 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - [Paper on Robert Frost], 1962 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - 5/15/63 Wood Program, 1963 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 1960-1965 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Minutes and Programs, 1966 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Programs, 1967 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, Assistant Recording Secretary, 1960-1969 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Minutes of Social Meetings, 1967-1970 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Financial Journal, Receipts and Disbursements, 1947-1966 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - 3x5 Cards of Members, 1961-1969 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - 1960s Yearbooks, 1960-1970 (Box 8, Folder 13)
- 1970-1980 (Box 9)
  Materials dated 1971-1980 are closed for research until 2045.
  - Minutes of Social Meetings, 1971-1978 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Executive Board and Annual Meeting Minutes, 1972-1980 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Program: "Shall We Join the Ladies" by J. M. Barrie, circa 1975 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Program Given by Emily Fisher at Chamber of Commerce at Liberty Street, circa 1972 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Program Given at Heights Casino - Walt Whitman, etc., circa 1972 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - 3/2/72 Meeting at Heights Casino "Words of Wisdom" Book Reports, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - 4/6/72 Meeting Script: "Dreams of Glory - Liberation 2072", 1972 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - 5/72 Meeting Trip to Lyndhurst, 1972 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - 1/11/73 Program: "Under Color Agent", 1973 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - 4/12/73 Program, 1973 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - 3/14/74 Program: "Aren't We Lucky", 1974 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - 4/11/74 Program: "Yes We Are", 1974 (Box 9, Folder 12)
  - Audrey Madden's Silver Lecture, 1978 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Minutes Assistant Recording Secretary, 1970-1973 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Programs, 1970-1979 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Programs, 1979-1980 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - Minutes of Social Meetings, 1979-1980 (Box 9, Folder 17)
  - 1970s Yearbooks, 1970-1979 (Box 9, Folder 18)
- 1979-1995 (Box 10)
  Materials dated 1981-1990 are closed for research until 2055. Materials dated 1991-1995 are closed for research until 2065.
  - Minutes of Social Meetings, 1981-1988 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Program: "Petunia's Perils", 1981 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Programs, 1982 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - 100th Anniversary Prep, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Centennial Celebration, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Past Presidents, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Programs, 1984-1985 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Programs, 1985-1987 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - 1/19/89 Eleanor Bachman Speech (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - 3/16/89 Mrs. Field's Musical "What's Love Got to do With It?", 1989 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - 4/20/89 Poetry "Parlez Moi d'Amour", 1989 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - Wrist Corsage Given to Each Guest at Centennial Meeting, 1984 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - Executive Board and Annual Meeting Minutes, 1981-1986 (Box 10, Folder 13)
  - Yearbooks, 1979-1995 (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Slides ["Perils of Petunia"], 1981 (Box 10, Folder 15)
  - Slides ["The Warrior's Husband"], 1982 (Box 10, Folder 16)
- 1984 (Box 11)
  Materials dated 1981-1990 are closed for research until 2055.
  - Centennial Celebration Photo Album, 1984 (Box 11, Folder 1)
- 1981-1984 (Box 12)
  - Side A: January 28, 1982, Judy Inglis Victorian Songs / Side B: April 1981 Faity Tuttle My Life in the Theatre, 1981-1982 (Box 12, Cassette 1)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Original Format: compact audio cassette, Duration: unknown
  - Mrs. Field's Centennial, Feb. 2, 1984 (Box 12, Cassette 2)
  - Perils of Pauline [Petunia], 1981 (Box 12, Cassette 3)
  - The Warrior's Husband, Mrs. Field's Literary Club, March 11, 1982 (Box 12, Cassette 4)
  - Side A: Jan. 22, 1981 China (Marty Rubin) / Side B: March 5, 1981 Perils of Petunia (Box 12, Cassette 5)
  - Side A: Mrs. Field's April 29 1982 / Side B: May 20, 1982, Music Barge [?], Peter Sanford (Box 12, Cassette 6)